Joseph W. Jacques Interviews
Joseph W. Jacques Interviews
1972-1973
Jacques, Joseph W.
1.0 linear ft.
Taped interviews with eleven leaders in the field of adult education, undertaken as part of Jacques's dissertation research. Interviews with Mary Armstrong, R.J. Blakely, Leland P. Bradford, Mary L. Collings, Paul L. Essert, Wilbur C. Hallenbeck, Samuel E. Hand, Andrew Hendrickson, Eugene I. Johnson, Howard Y. McClusky, and Ralph B. Spence. Also includes copy of Jacques' doctoral dissertation based on the interviews.
149078
Biographical History
Joseph W. Jacques, PhD in Adult Education, received his doctorate from Florida State University and later was on the faculty at Montclair State College. The interviews in this collection were conducted by Jacques as part of the basis for his doctoral dissertation.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Joseph W. Jacques Interviews consists of taped interviews and writings.
Interviews, conducted by Jacques as part of his research for his doctoral dissertation, are with eleven established leaders in the field of adult education in the United States: Mary Armstrong, Robert J. Blakely, Leland P. Bradford, Mary Louise Collings, Paul L. Essert, Wilbur C. Hallenbeck, Sam Hand, Andrew Hendrickson, Eugene I. Johnson, Howard Y. McClusky, and Ralph B. Spence. Following a format of structured questions, but allowing for free-wheeling discussion, Jacques' tapes probe the leaders' formative lives and educational experiences; their philosophies of living and of education; and their beliefs and opinions concerning current trends and the status of adult education in the United States. These 21 reels of recordings were made between March and May of 1972, and include much material not contained within Jacques' formal dissertation. The collection does not contain transcripts of the interviews.
Writings contains a copy of Jacques' doctoral dissertation which was based on the interviews and includes extensive excerpts.
Other Formats Available
Many of the tapes have been digitized. Contact the repository listed above for more information.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetically by interviewee.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing. In particular, see the Wilbur C. Hallenbeck Papers and the Andrew Hendrickson Papers.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Armstrong, Mary.; Blakely, Robert J.; Bradford, Leland P. (Leland Powers), 1905-1981.; Collings, Mary L.; Essert, Paul L.; Hallenbeck, Wilbur C. (Wilbur Chapman), 1892-1986.; Hand, Samuel E.; Hendrickson, Andrew, 1899-; Jacques, Joseph W.; Johnson, Eugene I.; McClusky, Howard Y., 1900-1982.; Spence, Ralph Beckett, 1901-1990.; Adult education -- United States.; Educators -- United States.; Sound recordings.; Audiocassettes.; Dissertations.; Oral histories (literary works); Tape reels.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Access to recordings may require advance notice for creation of a reading room copy.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joseph W. Jacques, 1976.
Inventory
- Interviews
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 1 - Armstrong, Collings], 3/19/1972; 5/8/1972; jacques_001; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Side #1 / Mary Armstrong 10 to 12 noon / her home - Union, New Jersey /March 19, 1972 / Side #2 Mary Louise Collings 2:30-4:00 PM / May 8, 1972, her living room - apartment
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 2 - Blakely], 4/22/1972; jacques_002; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #1 / Robert J. Blakely / Journalist / Adult educator / Adjunct Prof. - Syracuse / 9 AM to noon / April 22, 1972 / office Lib. of Cont’g Education / 107 Roney Lane, / Syracuse, NY / Interviewer - Historian / Joseph W. Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 3 - Bradford], 5/12/1972; jacques_003; Note on front of the box also lists: Essert; Hand; LCE; Johnson; Blakely (1); Collings; Armstrong; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Side 1 and 2: L. P. Bradford - Home, May 12, 1972, 3 PM - 5:15 PM; Joseph W. Jacques, Interviewer - Historian
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 4 - Essert], 3/22/1972; jacques_004; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Paul L. Essert / Adult Education / professor March 22 1972 / 10:30 AM to / 1:00 PM / Interviewer - Historian / Joseph W. Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 5 - Hallenbeck], 4/24/1972; jacques_005; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 64:31 (Box 1)
    Session #1 W. C. Hallenbeck / Home - 36 Seapit Rd / Waquoit, East Falmouth, / Mass. 02536 / April 24, 1972, / 2:30 PM to 6 PM / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 6 - Hallenbeck], 4/25/1972; jacques_006; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 129:00 (Box 1)
    Session #1 (cont’d) Hallenbeck / Session #2 Home - April 25, 1972 / 9:30 AM to 1 PM
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 7 - Hallenbeck], 4/26/1972; jacques_007; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 63:27 (Box 1)
    Session #2 (cont’d) Hallenbeck / Home April 26, 1972 / 9:30 am - 1:30 PM / Session #3 / Jacques / side #2 did not record
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 8 - Hallenbeck], 4/27/1972; jacques_008; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Hallenbeck / Session #3 (cont’d) / Session #4 / Home - April 27, 1972 / 9:30 AM to 12:15 PM / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 9 - Hand, Johnson], 5/17/1972; 5/30/1972; jacques_009; 1/4 inch audio tape; running time 120:10 (Box 1)
    Side #1 Dr. Sam Hand / Dir. Cont’g Education Office / Florida State Univ., Tallahassee / Interviewer-Historian, J. W. Jacques / May 30, 1972 / 9 AM - 11 AM / Side #2 Dr. Eugene I. Johnson / Adult Educator - Professor / office Fain Hall / Univ. of Georgia / Athens, Georgia / May 17, 1972, 4:30 PM - 6 PM
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 10 - Hendrickson], 6/5/1972; 6/9/1972; jacques_010; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Jacques / Session #1 6/5/72 - Andrew Hendrickson / 9:15-11:15 office - FSU - Dep’t of Adult Education / Session #6 6/9/72 10:30-11 AM office
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 11 - Hendrickson], 6/6/1972; 6/7/1972; jacques_011; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #2 Hendrickson - office / June 6, 1972 / 9:15 AM-11:15 AM / Session #3 June 7, 1972 / office / 10 AM to 11:45 AM / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 12 - Hendrickson], 6/8/1972; jacques_012; Note on the box reads: "Hendrickson #7".; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #3 (cont’d) Hendrickson / Session #4 office / 9:15 - 11:15 AM / June 8, 1972 / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 13 - Hendrickson], 6/8/1972; jacques_013; Note in red marker: "Messed up".; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #4 (cont’d) Hendrickson / Session #5 Hendrickson office / 9:15 to 11:15 AM / Jacques
  - Dr. Eugene Johnson Tape 1, 5/17/1972; jacques_022; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2)
    Dr. Eugene Johnson / Adult Educator-Professor / Univ. of Georgia / May 17, 1972
  - Dr. Eugene Johnson Tape 2, 5/17/1972; jacques_023; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 2)
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 14 - McClusky], 4/10/1972; 4/11/1972; jacques_014; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #1 McClusky - adult ed. professor / 10 AM to 11 AM /motel room April 10, 1972 / Session #2 motel room / 10:30 AM to noon April 11, 1972 / Interviewer-Historian / Jos. W. Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 15 - McClusky], 4/12/1972; jacques_015; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #3 McClusky / Session #2 (cont’d) April 12, 1972 / motel room / 3:30 PM 5:30 PM / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 16 - McClusky], 4/12/1972; 4/13/1972; jacques_016; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
    Session #3 (cont’d) / McClusky / motel - April 12, 1972 / Session #4 / motel / April 13th, ‘72 / 1:30 PM - 5 PM / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 17 - McClusky], 4/13/1972; 4/14/1972; jacques_017; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
    Session #4 (cont’d) / McClusky / motel - April 13, ‘72 / 1:50 PM - 5 PM / Session #5 / motel / April 14, ‘72 / 1:30 PM - 4 PM / Jacques
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 18 - Spence], 5/15/1972; jacques_018; Note on box reads: "Spence No. 1; Blakely, take No. 2".; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
    Session #1 / Dr. Ralph Beckett Spence / Office - Fain Hall / Univ. of Georgia / May 15, 1972 9 AM - 11 AM / Session #2 / Home of respondent / 355 Beechwood Drive, / Athens, Georgia
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 19 - Spence], May 15-16, 1972; jacques_019; "Spence No. 2". Note on back of the box reads: "Tape can be used - re-tape to tape No. 1".; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
    Session #2 Spence / (cont’d) / Respondent’s home / 3 PM to 6 PM / May 15, 1972 / Session #3 / office / 11 AM to 12 noon / May 16, 1972 / Session #4 / home - 3 PM to 5 PM / May 16, 1972
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 20 - Spence], 5/16/1972; jacques_020; "Spence No. 3".; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
    Spence - Session #4 / home - 3 PM to 5 PM / May 16, 1972 / Session #5 / office 9:30 AM to 11:30 AM
  - [Joseph W. Jacques Interviews reel 21 - Spence, Blakely], 5/17/1972; jacques_021; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 2)
    Side #1 / Session #5 / Spence / office 9:30 AM to 12 noon / May 17, 1972 / Side #2 / Session cont’d / Blakely / Jacques
- Writings
  - Recollections and reflections of professors of adult education: Early 20th century leaders and pioneers in the field, 1973; dissertation, Florida State University, for PhD in adult education; 1 volume (Box 3)